[
    {
        "question": "(<em>ic</em>) #### eom geanwyrde monuc⁠ — I am a professed monk",
        "correctAnswer": "ic",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the nominative so it remains 'ic'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hwæt sægest (<em>þu</em>) ####, yrþlingc?⁠ — What say you, farmer?",
        "correctAnswer": "þu",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the nominative so it remains 'þu'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>he</em>) #### Noe gebletsade and his bearn⁠ — He blessed Noah and his child",
        "correctAnswer": "he",
        "explanation":"Here 'he' is used in the nominative so it remains 'he'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Drihtnes ys eorðe, and eall þæt (<em>heo</em>) #### mid gefyld is⁠ — The earth is the Lord's, and all that she is filled with",
        "correctAnswer": "heo",
        "explanation":"Here 'heo' is used in the nominative so it remains 'heo'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>we</em>) #### cildra biddaþ þe, eala lareow, þæt þu tæce us sprecan leden⁠ — We children ask you, oh teacher, that you teach us to speak Latin",
        "correctAnswer": "we",
        "explanation":"Here 'we' is used in the nominative so it remains 'we'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif (<em>ge</em>) #### me ut adrifaþ fram eowrum geferscype ge etaþ wyrta eowre grene ond flæscmettas eowre hreawe⁠ — If you drive me away from your community you would eat your vegetables raw and your meat rare",
        "correctAnswer": "ge",
        "explanation":"Here 'ge' is used in the nominative so it remains 'ge'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>hie</em>) #### gretton hie gesybsumum wordum⁠ — They greeted them with words of peace",
        "correctAnswer": "hie",
        "explanation":"Here 'hie' is used in the nominative so it remains 'hie'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ealle þing (<em>ic</em>) #### synt gesealde⁠ — All things are given by me",
        "correctAnswer": "me",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the accusative so it becomes 'me'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We (<em>þu</em>) #### þanciaþ, þe þu hafest on gewealdum hiofen and eorþan⁠ — We thank you, you who has control of heaven and earth",
        "correctAnswer": "þe",
        "explanation":"Here 'þe' is used in the accusative so it becomes 'þe'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He (<em>he</em>) #### miclum gewundode⁠ — He wounded him severely",
        "correctAnswer": "hine",
        "explanation":"Here 'he' is used in the accusative so it becomes 'hine'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He geseah (<em>heo</em>) #### feorran⁠ — He saw her from afar",
        "correctAnswer": "heo",
        "explanation":"Here 'heo' is used in the accusative but feminine third person singular pronouns do not decline differently between nominiative and accusative so it stays as 'heo'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se abbod nerede (<em>we</em>) ####⁠ — The abbod saved us",
        "correctAnswer": "us",
        "explanation":"Here 'we' is used in the accusative so it becomes 'us'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic hiere (<em>ge</em>) #### Suþ-Dena folc⁠ — I hear you, people of the South-Danes",
        "correctAnswer": "eow",
        "explanation":"Here 'ge' is used in the accusative so it becomes 'eow'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie æt Tharse ðære byrig hie gemetton ond hie ða (<em>hie</em>) #### gecyston⁠ — They met one another at the city of Tarsus and they then kissed them",
        "correctAnswer": "hie",
        "explanation":"Here 'hie' is used in the accusative but third person plural pronouns do not decline differently between nominiative and accusative so it stays as 'hie'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hwanon sylan scear oþþe culter, þe na gade hæfþ buton of cræfte (<em>ic</em>) ####?⁠ — How does the ploughman get his plough-share or knife or goad but by my craft? ",
        "correctAnswer": "min",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the genitive so it becomes 'min'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðonne þu and (<em>þu</em>) #### beoþ alysde⁠ — When you are yours are released",
        "correctAnswer": "þin",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the genitive so it becomes 'þin'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða he gefor ða feng (<em>he</em>) #### sunu to ðam rice⁠ — When he died then came his son to the throne",
        "correctAnswer": "his",
        "explanation":"Here 'he' is used in the genitive so it becomes 'his'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He (<em>heo</em>) #### hand nam and heo sona aras⁠ — He took her hand and she arose at once",
        "correctAnswer": "hire",
        "explanation":"Here 'heo' is used in the genitive so it becomes 'hire'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We sceolan syllan ðone teoþan dæl (<em>we</em>) #### worldspeda⁠ — We shall give the tenth portion of our world's goods",
        "correctAnswer": "ure",
        "explanation":"Here 'we' is used in the genitive so it becomes 'ure'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þa Gotan eow hwon oferhergedon, and (<em>ge</em>) #### feawe ofslogon⁠ — The Ostrogoths ravaged you a little and slew a few of you",
        "correctAnswer": "eower",
        "explanation":"Here 'ge' is used in the genitive so it becomes 'eower'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða cuædon hie ðæt him nænig mæg leofra nære ðonne (<em>hie</em>) #### hlaford⁠ — Then they said that to them, no kinsman was dearer than their lord",
        "correctAnswer": "hira",
        "explanation":"Here 'hie' is used in the genitive so it becomes 'hira'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic be (<em>ic</em>) #### secge ðis sarspell⁠ — I tell this lament about myself",
        "correctAnswer": "me",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the dative so it becomes 'me'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic wille wiþ (<em>þu</em>) #### farnan, Ælfirc⁠ — I will go with you, Alfric",
        "correctAnswer": "þe",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the dative so it becomes 'þe'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se arcebiscop axode hyrsumnesse mid aþswerunge at (<em>he</em>) ####⁠ — The archbishop asked for obedience with an oath to him",
        "correctAnswer": "him",
        "explanation":"Here 'he' is used in the dative so it becomes 'him'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo spræc to (<em>heo</em>) #### selfre suna⁠ — She spoke to her own sons",
        "correctAnswer": "hire",
        "explanation":"Here 'heo' is used in the dative so it becomes 'hire'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ure fæder geaf to (<em>we</em>) #### feower bec fram feowerum foldan sceatum⁠ — Our father gave to us four books from the four corners of the world",
        "correctAnswer": "us",
        "explanation":"Here 'we' is used in the dative so it becomes 'us'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Sibb sy mid (<em>ge</em>) ####⁠ — Peace be with ye",
        "correctAnswer": "eow",
        "explanation":"Here 'ge' is used in the dative so it becomes 'eow'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie woldon ða men (<em>hie</em>) #### to mete don⁠ — They wanted the men to make food for themselves",
        "correctAnswer": "heom",
        "explanation":"Here 'hie' is used in the dative so it becomes 'heom'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Abram cwæð to Lothe '(<em>ic</em>) #### sind gebroðru⁠ — Abraham said to Lot: 'We two are brothers'",
        "correctAnswer": "wit",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual nominative so it becomes 'wit'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wit (<em>ic</em>) #### in ðære burnan baðodan⁠ — We two washed ourselves in that brook",
        "correctAnswer": "unc",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual accusative so it becomes 'unc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Crist þonne wat (<em>ic</em>) #### clænnyss⁠ — Christ is the water of our purity",
        "correctAnswer": "uncer",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual genitive so it becomes 'uncer'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Nu ic eom orwena ðæt (<em>ic</em>) #### seo eðylstæf afre weorþe gifede ætgædere⁠ — Now I am hopeless that the staff of our family will ever be given to us two together",
        "correctAnswer": "unc",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual dative so it becomes 'unc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif (<em>þu</em>) #### ðæt fæsten fyre willaþ forstandan⁠ — If you two will protect that fastness from fire",
        "correctAnswer": "git",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual nominative so it becomes 'git'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Swa (<em>þu</em>) #### se balewa het⁠ — So the baleful one commanded you two ",
        "correctAnswer": "inc",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual accusative so it becomes 'inc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic nu ðis þing write to ðe gemanelice and to minre meder and minum geswustrum forðon (<em>þu</em>) #### lufu sceal beon somod gemane⁠ — I now write this thing to you together, to my mother and my sister, because the love of you both shall be mutual ",
        "correctAnswer": "incer",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual genitive so it becomes 'incer'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hwæt wylle git ðæt ic (<em>þu</em>) #### do?⁠ — What do you two wish I do for you two?",
        "correctAnswer": "inc",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual dative so it becomes 'inc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða wæron (<em>ic</em>) #### twegen on anum olfende þurh þæt rume westen⁠ — Then we two were on a camel travelling through that enormous desert",
        "correctAnswer": "wit",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual nominative so it becomes 'wit'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>ic</em>) #### he bitere forgeald⁠ — He bitterly repaid us",
        "correctAnswer": "unc",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual accusative so it becomes 'unc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðanne gæornlicæ of þam god geþæncæ and for (<em>ic</em>) #### sawle geornlicæ beo⁠ — Remember God diligently from the property and be diligent for our two souls",
        "correctAnswer": "uncer",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual genitive so it becomes 'uncer'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>ic</em>) #### is his hyldo þearf⁠ — for us two his favour is a necessity ",
        "correctAnswer": "unc",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual dative so it becomes 'unc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þu</em>) #### sindon bigswicon⁠ — You two are deceivers",
        "correctAnswer": "git",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual nominative so it becomes 'git'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>þu</em>) #### forgeaf balewe geþohtas⁠ — He inspired you with wicked thoughts",
        "correctAnswer": "inc",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual accusative so it becomes 'inc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ac git waron æt þisse wydewan hame and þær þus (<em>þu</em>) #### lif leofodon⁠ — But you were at the home of a widow, and there passed your time in wisdom",
        "correctAnswer": "incer",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual genitive so it becomes 'incer'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>ic</em>) #### her baru standaþ unwered wædo⁠ — we two stand here naked, unprotected by garments",
        "correctAnswer": "wit",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual nominative so it becomes 'wit'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wit (<em>ic</em>) #### gefyldan niowes ceses⁠ — We filled ourselves with new cheese",
        "correctAnswer": "unc",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual accusative so it becomes 'unc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wit geseagon (<em>ic</em>) #### feond forwordene⁠ — We two saw our enemy perish",
        "correctAnswer": "uncer",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual genitive so it becomes 'uncer'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God mæg foreaðe (<em>ic</em>) #### æt foresceawian⁠ — God can very easily provide food for us two",
        "correctAnswer": "unc",
        "explanation":"Here 'ic' is used in the first person dual dative so it becomes 'unc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": " Gangaþ ut (<em>þu</em>) #### godwrecan⁠ — Come out ye two wretches",
        "correctAnswer": "git",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual nominative so it becomes 'git'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þu</em>) #### sceal worn fela maðma gemænra⁠ — To you two shall be a great many common treasures",
        "correctAnswer": "inc",
        "explanation":"Here 'þu' is used in the first person dual dative so it becomes 'inc'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þa cwæð God nis na gedafenlic þæt #### man ana beo⁠ — Then God said 'it is not fitting that this man be alone'",
        "correctAnswer": "þes|ðes",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular masculine nominative 'man' so it stays as 'þes'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þa gefæstnode he #### ræd wið þæt werod þe he bewiste, and hie ealle to ðam ræde gebugon⁠ — Then he confirmed this resolve with the host over which he ruled, and they all bowed to that resolve",
        "correctAnswer": "þisne|ðisne",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular masculine accusative 'ræd' so it becomes 'þisne'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ac se wurðmynt wæs #### dæges mærðe gehealden, þæt hie mid heofenlicum leohte hie geswutelodon⁠ — But that honour was reserved for the greatness of this day, that they should manifest themselves with heavenly light",
        "correctAnswer": "þisses",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular masculine genitive 'dæg' so it becomes 'þisses'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On Godes naman ahreose #### templ mid eallum þam deofolgyldum þe him on eardiað⁠ — In the name of God, let this temple fall with all the idols that dwell within it",
        "correctAnswer": "þis",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular neuter nominative 'templ' so it becomes 'þis'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Nim #### cild mid þære meder and fleoh to Egypta lande⁠ — Take this child with the mother and flee to Egypt",
        "correctAnswer": "þis",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular neuter accusative 'cild' so it becomes 'þis'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Adam þa wæs wunigende on #### life mid geswince, and he and his wif ða bearn gestryndon⁠ — Adam then was continuing in this life with toil, and he and his wife begat children",
        "correctAnswer": "þissum",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular neuter dative 'life' so it becomes 'þissum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Widewe wæs #### Anna, þe we gefyrn ær embe spræcon⁠ — This Anna was a widow who we have spoken of before",
        "correctAnswer": "þeos",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular feminine nominative 'Anna' so it becomes 'þeos'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "þas",
                "explanation": "Though the word order is confusing, Anna is the subject, not the object of 'wæs' so it takes the singular nominative feminine 'þeos'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Send me þinne engel on fyrenum wolcne þæt þa embgange ealle #### ceastre þæt ne magen geneosian for þsem fyre⁠ — Send me your angel from heaven in a fiery cloud that he my encompass all this city",
        "correctAnswer": "þas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular feminine accusative 'ceaster' so it becomes 'þas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þæt sædon gehwilce wise lareowas þæt hie habbað gefremod heora ærist to ðam ecan lífe swa swa we ealle don sceolon on ende #### worulde⁠ —  All wise teachers have said that they have effected their resurrection to eternal life, as we all shall do at the end of this world",
        "correctAnswer": "þisre",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular feminine genitive 'worulde' so it becomes 'þisre'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Oft ys seo halige þrinnys geswutelod on #### boc⁠ — Often is the holy trinity revealed in this book",
        "correctAnswer": "þisre",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the singular feminine dative 'boc' so it becomes 'þisre'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "#### ðing we ne magon don butan earfoðnyssum⁠ — These things we cannot do without difficulty",
        "correctAnswer": "þas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the plural neuter nominative 'ðing' so it becomes 'þas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Nimað þis gold ond #### gymstanas ond farað ond bicgað eow landare⁠ — Take this gold and these gemstones and go and buy yourself land",
        "correctAnswer": "þas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the plural neuter accusative 'gymstan' so it becomes 'þas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "#### læssan giefa þæt sind þa fugelas þe wæron wannspedigra manna giefa wæron for Criste geoffrode⁠ — These smaller gifts, that is the birds which were the gifts of indigent persons, were offered for Christ",
        "correctAnswer": "þas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the plural feminine nominative 'giefu' so it becomes 'þas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On ðære ealdan æ is gehwær gesett, þæt God het gelomlice #### fugelas offrian on his lace⁠ — In the old law it is in several places mentioned, that God frequently commanded these birds to be offered to him in sacrifice",
        "correctAnswer": "þas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the plural masculine accusative 'fugel' so it becomes 'þas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Eala hu rihtlice hie andetton þone halgan geleafan mid #### wordum: On frymðe wæs word, and þæt word wæs mid Gode⁠ — O how rightly they acknowledged the holy faith with these words, 'In the beginning was the word, and the word was with God'",
        "correctAnswer": "þissum",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the plural neuter dative 'word' so it becomes 'þissum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif ðu Godes Sunu sy wend #### stanas to hlafum ond et⁠ — If you are the son of god, turn these stones to loaves and eat",
        "correctAnswer": "þas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þes' is modifying the plural masculine accusative 'gymstan' so it becomes 'þas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þissum dagum (<em>se</em>) #### micel þegen ferde eft to Englalande — On this day that mighty thane went again to England",
        "correctAnswer": "se",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'se' because it is tied to the subject 'þegen'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "In (<em>se</em>) #### cyninges tune — In that town of the king",
        "correctAnswer": "þæs",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæs' because it is tied to 'cyning' which has the genitive singular 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ferþ to (<em>se</em>) #### tune — The king goes to that town",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to 'tun' which has the dative singular 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>se</em>) #### biscopas geaf þone stan to þaem þegne — Those bishops gave the stone to the thane",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the subject 'biscop' which has the plural 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ond seo cwen gretton (<em>se</em>) #### biscopas — The king and the queen greeted those bishops",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to 'biscop' which has the plural 'as' ending and is the direct recipient of the verb 'grete'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>se</em>) #### wicinga cyning wolde þæt þa Deniscan ricsoden ofer Englalande — That king of vikings willed that the Danes ruled over England",
        "correctAnswer": "þara",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þara' because it is tied to 'wicing' which has the genetive plural ending 'a'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se geaf þa garas to (<em>se</em>) #### þegnum — He gave the spear to those thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to 'þegnum' which has the dative plural 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>se</em>) #### biscop wæs halig and eaþmod — That bishop was holy and humble",
        "correctAnswer": "se",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'se' because it is tied to the subject 'biscop'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen sloh (<em>se</em>) #### biscop in þæm tune genemed Stanford — The thane slew that bishop in the town called Stamford",
        "correctAnswer": "þone",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þone' because it is tied to 'biscop' which is directly receiving the action of the verb 'sloh'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða bearn (<em>se</em>) #### cyninges beoþ wis and eaþmod — The children of that king are wise and humble",
        "correctAnswer": "þæs",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæs' because it is tied to 'cyning' which has the genitive singular 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þissum geare sende he þone ealdan biscop Wulfstan to (<em>se</em>) #### stede þe genemened Readingum — On this year he sent the old Bishop Wulfstan to that place which was called Reading",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to 'stede'. While 'stede' already ends in an e, making it hard to tell the case, it is after the preposition 'to' and indirectly receiving the action which makes it dative",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>se</em>) #### biscopas comon fram þæm tunum hetum Londenum ond Readingum — Those bishops came from the towns called London and Reading",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the subject 'biscop' which has the plural 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gaþ! Fliemaþ (<em>se</em>) #### Englas and timbriaþ fela tuna on hiera landum — Go! Banish those English and build many towns on their land",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to 'Englas' which has the plural 'as' ending and is the direct recipient of the verb 'fliemaþ'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Eall (<em>se</em>) #### biscopa preostas ferde to þæm halige stede mid him — All those bishops’ priests went to the holy place with them",
        "correctAnswer": "þara",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þara' because it is tied to 'biscopa' which has the genetive plural ending 'a'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He cwæð þæt he bude on (<em>se</em>) #### landum norþweardum wiþ þa Westsæ — He said that he lived in those lands northward along the west sea",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to 'land' which has the dative plural 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Giet wæs (<em>se</em>) #### cyning Aelfred geong — Still, that king Alfred was young",
        "correctAnswer": "se",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'se' because it is tied to the subject 'cyning'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ælfric geaf (<em>se</em>) #### æþeling drync — Aelfric gave that prince a drink",
        "correctAnswer": "þone",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þone' because it is tied to 'æþeling' which is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He geaf (<em>se</em>) #### æþelinges begas to þære cwene — He gave that prince's rings to the queen",
        "correctAnswer": "þæs",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæs' because it is tied to 'æþeling' which has the genitive singular 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se abbot com fram (<em>se</em>) #### beorgum — The abbot came from those mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation": "Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to 'beorg' which has the dative plural 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þæt</em>) #### scip sceal genægled — That ship must be nailed",
        "correctAnswer": "þæt",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæt' because it is tied to the subject 'scip'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þæt</em>) #### wif wæs gehæled of ðam wite — That woman was healed of the disease",
        "correctAnswer": "þæt",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæt' because it is tied to the subject 'wif'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þæt</em>) #### bearn is min dohtor — That child is my daughter",
        "correctAnswer": "þæt",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæt' because it is tied to the subject 'bearn'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif (<em>þæt</em>) #### word sind soþ — If those words are true",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural subject 'word'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þæt</em>) #### scipu ferde to þæm stede — Those ships went to that place",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural subject 'scipu'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þæt</em>) #### godu fram Egiptum landum beoþ fremede godu — Those gods from Egypt are strange gods",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural subject 'godu'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He spræc to (<em>þæt</em>) #### wif — He spoke to that woman",
        "correctAnswer": "þæt",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæt' because it is tied to the singular direct object 'wif'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se preost gebletsade (<em>þæt</em>) #### scip — The priest blessed that ship",
        "correctAnswer": "þæt",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæt' because it is tied to the singular direct object 'scip'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning geaf (<em>þæt</em>) #### scip to his suna — The king gave that ship to his son",
        "correctAnswer": "þæt",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæt' because it is tied to the singular direct object 'scip'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He wolde geseean (<em>þæt</em>) #### godu — He wanted to visit those gods",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural direct object 'godu'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se mann seah (<em>þæt</em>) #### wif — The man saw that women",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural direct object 'wif'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þæt</em>) #### scipes mæst geburnen — That ship's mast burned",
        "correctAnswer": "þæs",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæs' because it is tied to the possessive 'scipes'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He geaf (<em>þæt</em>) #### wifes boc to þæm biscop — He gave that woman's book to the bishop",
        "correctAnswer": "þæs",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæs' because it is tied to the possessive 'wifes'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>þæt</em>) #### fremede godes preost bædon to his gode — That strange god's priest prayed to his god",
        "correctAnswer": "þæs",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæs' because it is tied to the possessive 'godes'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þis dæg, com (<em>þæt</em>) #### hæthenes goda wigan — On that day, those warriors of the heathen gods came",
        "correctAnswer": "þara",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þara' because it is tied to the plural possessive 'goda'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He geaf (<em>þæt</em>) #### bearna bec to his suna — He gave those childrens books to his son",
        "correctAnswer": "þara",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þara' because it is tied to the plural possessive 'bearna'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo cwen geaf þa boc to (<em>þæt</em>) #### wife — The queen gave the book to that woman",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the indirect object 'wife'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning spræc to (<em>þæt</em>) #### bearne — The king spoke to that child",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the indirect object 'bearne'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða menn ferde to (<em>þæt</em>) #### scipe mid þæm sceattum — Those men went to that ship with the treasure",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the indirect object 'scipe'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo geaf micel giefa to (<em>þæt</em>) #### wifum — She gave many gifts to those women",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the indirect object 'wifum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se here ferde to (<em>þæt</em>) #### scipum — The army went to those ships",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the indirect object 'scipum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se preost bædon to (<em>þæt</em>) #### godum — The priest prayed to those gods",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the indirect object 'godum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### cwen ferþ to þæm beorgum — That queen goes to the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "seo",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'seo' because it is tied to the subject 'cwen'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### ceaster ne mæg beon behyd — That city cannot be hidden",
        "correctAnswer": "seo",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'seo' because it is tied to the subject 'ceaster'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### giefu wæs swiþe geæhted — That gift was greatly prized",
        "correctAnswer": "seo",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'seo' because it is tied to the subject 'giefu'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### cwena wæron hatene Marsepia and Lampida — Those queens were called Marsepia and Lampida",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural subject 'cwena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### ceastra, Gleawanceaster, Cirenceaster and Baþanceaster, beoþ on ceastrum weallum beworhte — Those cities, Gloucester, Cirencester and Bath, are walled towns",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural subject 'ceastra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### idesa sloh ða wundenlocc þone feondsceaðan — That women slew the wavy—haired fiend",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural subject 'idesa'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ælla and Cissa ymbsæton (<em>seo</em>) #### ceastre — Aella and Cissa beseiged that city",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the singular direct object 'ceastre'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He lufast (<em>seo</em>) #### idese — He loves that lady",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the singular direct object 'idese'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic hierde (<em>seo</em>) #### cwen — I heard that queen",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the singular direct object 'cwen'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo geaf (<em>seo</em>) #### giefa to þæm werum — She gave those gifts to the men",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural direct object 'giefa'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas neredon (<em>seo</em>) #### idesa — Those thanes saved those ladies",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural direct object 'idesa'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas læston (<em>seo</em>) #### cwena — The thanes followed those Queens",
        "correctAnswer": "þa",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þa' because it is tied to the plural direct object 'cwena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### ceastre ealdorman spræc mid þæm biscope — That city's elderman spoke with the bishop",
        "correctAnswer": "þære",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þære' because it is tied to the possessive 'ceastre'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He wæs on (<em>seo</em>) #### cwena gewealdum — He was under the power of those queens",
        "correctAnswer": "þara",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þara' because it is tied to the plural possessive 'cwena'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>seo</em>) #### ceastra wisra menn ferde to þæm cyning — The wise men of those cities went to the king ",
        "correctAnswer": "þara",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þara' because it is tied to the plural possessive 'ceastra'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie to (<em>seo</em>) #### cwene agefon him — They gave him up to that queen",
        "correctAnswer": "þære",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þære' because it is tied to the indirect object 'cwene'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas ferde to (<em>seo</em>) #### idese — The thanes went to that lady",
        "correctAnswer": "þære",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þære' because it is tied to the indirect object 'idese'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða comon ða weardas to (<em>seo</em>) #### ceastre — Then the keepers came into that city",
        "correctAnswer": "þære",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þære' because it is tied to the indirect object 'ceastre'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hlynn wearþ on (<em>seo</em>) #### ceastrum — A great cry arose in those cities",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the plural indirect object 'ceastrum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He geaf þa bec to (<em>seo</em>) #### idesum — He gave the books to those ladies",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the plural indirect object 'idesum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas geaf begas ond feoh to (<em>seo</em>) #### cwenum — The thanes gave rings and wealth to those queens",
        "correctAnswer": "þæm",
        "explanation":"Here the demonstrative pronoun is 'þæm' because it is tied to the plural indirect object 'cwenum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]